This is a demo of the design probe used in our
interviews for the IEEE VIS 2024 submission, "What
can interactive visualization do for participatory
budgeting in Chicago?" Hereafter, we refer to
participatory budgeting as PB. Participants first
landed on this page which gives them information
about the PB process in Chicago and gives the
opportunity to enter a user ID for logging
interaction data. Our probe elicits preferences
for proposed municipal projects in three stages:
sorting, allocating, and checking allocations.
On the sort page, participants are introduced
to the proposed projects on the PB ballot. We
pulled these projects descriptions and their
costs (which we reveal later) from a synthesis of
actual PB ballots from previous years in Chicago.
Participants can order and reorder
projects using a flexible drag interaction.
When the participant is happy with their sort
order for all projects, they can move on.
On the allocation page, participants are asked
to draw a distribution of funding by dragging
on the bars in the chart. Projects appear in
the short order from the the previous page.
Participants can use the "clear" and "fill
up" buttons to fine-tune their allocations,
exactly reaching a total
budget amount of $1 million.
On the check allocations page, the estimated
cost of each project is revealed as rule
markings colored to indicate which
projects have received sufficient
funding. The participant's allocations from
the previous page persist. Participants have
the option of revising their allocation
now that costs are known. Now a "set to
cost" button appears below each bar to
aid in hitting the exact cost estimate.
Participants do not have enough money to fund all
projects fully so they have
some hard choices to make.
Participants fill out an
optional demographic survey.
The final page of the application provides
a dashboard of simulated voting results. The
heatmap shows demographic data about voters in
each ward versus the census. Participants can
select different Wards to compare by clicking
the map or by using the drop- down menu.
They can also view vote and census counts
rather than normalized percentages. This
emphasizes how many people in the ward have
voted rather than demographic representation.
Participants can also view how people
voted within and across wards. The strip
plot shows final allocations for categories
of PB projects such as biking and transit
or streets and sidewalks, with each mark
representing the allocations of one voter.
PB projects are binned into categories
to facilitate comparisons across wards,
where residents will have voted
on different sets of projects. Our
intention was that voters might return to a
page like this to monitor election results